{"tossups": [{"question": "This country took five boats from a French port in the Cherbourg Project; France had refused to deliver the boats, for which this country had paid, when diplomatic relations broke after the Six-Day War. Operation Wrath of God was launched after 11 members of this country\u2019s Olympic team were killed in 1972. For the point, name this Middle Eastern country that carried out those missions via Mossad, an intelligence agency that reports to Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu.", "answer": "<b> Israel</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This location became inhabited after the Battle of White Marsh. A legend about this location relates how Isaac Potts encountered a general praying in the snow. Flour and water was mixed to form \u201cfirecake\u201dat this site, where a<em> Blue Book</em> was produced after the arrival of Baron von Steuben, who taught military drill to its inhabitants. For the point, name this Pennsylvania site where the Continental Army endured the winter of 1777.", "answer": "<b> Valley Forge</b> (prompt on Pennsylvania)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The \u201cSix Philosophies\u201d of this modern country\u2019s classical philosophy can be broadly categorized into schools referred to as \u201cthere exists\u201d and \u201cthere doesn\u2019t exist.\u201d Sources of knowledge in this country\u2019s philosophy are known as pramanas. The grammarian Panini worked in this modern-day country, whose <em>Upanishads</em> greatly influenced the work of Arthur Schopenhauer. For the point, name this modern country whose non-violent philosophies include<em> ahimsa</em> and Mahatma Gandhi\u2019s<em> satyagraha</em>.", "answer": "Republic of<b> India</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "This artist painted a group of school children looking at a bust of Lenin in<em> Russian Schoolroom</em>. In another painting by this artist, a tomato is splattered against the wall while four U.S. Marshals escort Ruby Bridges to a desegregated school. This artist of<em> The Problem We All Live With</em> depicted a woman serving a turkey dinner to her family. For the point, name this artist of the<em> Four Freedom</em> series, who designed many covers for the<em> Saturday Evening Post</em>.", "answer": "Norman (Perceval)<b> Rockwell</b> Page 1", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A 1974 coup d\u2019etat in this country led to the downfall of another country\u2019s Regime of the Colonels. The guerilla group EOKA in this country was led by its first President, Makarios III, and by Georgios Grivas, an advocate of the<em> enosis</em> policy that would unite this country with Greece. For the point, name this Mediterranean island country where a buffer zone divides Turkish and Greek-controlled territory and a Green Line runs through its capital, Nicosia.", "answer": "Republic of<b> Cyprus</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In 1829, this commodity caused a \u201cGreat Intrusion\u201d into modern-day Lumpkin County near Dahlonega [duh-LAH-na-guh], Georgia. Jim Fisk and Jay Gould\u2019s attempt to corner this commodity\u2019s market caused a Black Friday in 1869. Two years before the Battle of Little Bighorn, General George Custer led forces into South Dakota to search for, for the point, what precious metal whose discovery at Sutter\u2019s Mill triggered a namesake \u201crush\u201d to California in 1848?", "answer": "<b> gold</b> (accept elaborations, like<b> gold</b> mining)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This event spurred the creation of a show hosted by Frank Reynolds, ABC\u2019s<em> Nightline</em>. Cyrus Vance resigned during this event after disagreements over a botched helicopter rescue mission, Operation Eagle Claw. Canadian Ambassador Ken Taylor sheltered six people who escaped this event by posing as a film crew. This event ended on the day of Ronald Reagan\u2019s inauguration. For the point, name this event in which American citizens were held for 444 days in Tehran.", "answer": "<b> Iran Hostage</b> Crisis", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This phrase names a terrorist \u201cFaction\u201d led by Baader and Meinhof in West Germany. Zhu De led a force of this name that was labeled for \u201cWorkers and Peasants\u201d until after World War II; that force fought five counter-encirclement campaigns against Chiang Kai-shek\u2019s Nationalists. The arrival of another force of this name in Berlin forced Hitler to commit suicide. For the point, give this colorful term for land-based military forces in Bolshevik Russia and Communist China.", "answer": "<b> Red Army</b> (accept<b> Red Army</b> Faction; accept Chinese<b> Red Army</b>; accept Soviet<b> Red Army</b> or descriptions thereof; prompt on partial answers; prompt on Chinese army after \u201cZhu De\u201d is read; prompt on Soviet army after \u201cBerlin\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The terms ratified during this event had earlier been tabled in the Treaty of Chaumont. The Earl of Clancarty was sent to this event after military hostilities broke out during it. This conference, which attempted to restore monarchs to their pre-war thrones, was interrupted by the Hundred Days when a French emperor returned to power. Klemens von Metternich chaired, for the point, what 1814 \u201cCongress\u201dto restore order after the Napoleonic Wars, held in Austria?", "answer": "<b> Congress of Vienna</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "George Tucker wrote an 1836 biography of this man, who had earlier asked Tucker to serve as a Moral Philosophy professor. This man won a presidential election after a compromise secured James Bayard\u2019s decisive electoral college vote. This man obtained an over 45 percent margin in the popular vote in the first post-12th Amendment presidential election. The first president from the Democratic-Republican party was, for the point, what man who first won the presidency in 1800 over incumbent John Adams?", "answer": "Thomas<b> Jefferson</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This composer set a description of Solomon\u2019s anointing for an anthem that has been played at the coronation of every British monarch since George II. This composer of<em> Zadok The Priest</em> included the chorus \u201cSee the conqu\u2019ring hero comes\u201d in his oratorio<em> Judas Maccabaeus</em>. King George II supposedly began the tradition of standing during another work of this composer. For the point, name this German-born composer who included the \u201cHallelujah Chorus\u201d in his<em> Messiah</em>.", "answer": "George Frideric<b> Handel</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This region\u2019s development grew under the Dalstroy construction trust, which operated slave labor for the NKVD. In this region, the port city of Magadan developed to ship mined materials from the Kolyma Gulag. A railroad named for this region once required a ferry to cross Lake Baikal and now spans the distance from Moscow to Vladivostok. For the point, name this eastern region of Russia where Stalin operated many prisons in isolated, cold conditions.", "answer": "<b> Siberia</b> (accept Trans-<b>Siberia</b>n Railroad after \u201crailroad\u201d is read; prompt on (eastern) Russia)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "An army led by this man defeated forces under David Leslie at the Battle of Dunbar, after which he captured the city of Edinburgh. This man\u2019s power was affirmed by John Lambert\u2019s Instrument of Government shortly after this man had created and then dissolved Barebone\u2019s Parliament. This man ruled over the Protectorate after his faction, the Roundheads, defeated the faction of Charles I in the English Civil War. For the point, name this Puritan leader and Lord Protector of England.", "answer": "Oliver<b> Cromwell</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 1971, the Supreme Court unanimously overturned this man\u2019s conviction for refusing to join the Army; in his refusal, this man cited his Muslim beliefs and the fact that he \u201cain\u2019t got no quarrel with them Viet Cong.\u201d This man opposed George Foreman in the 1974 \u201cRumble in the Jungle,\u201d knocking him out in the 8th round. For the point, name this boxer, born Cassius Clay, who was known as \u201cthe Greatest\u201dand died in 2016 after a lengthy battle with Parkinson\u2019s.", "answer": "Muhammad<b> Ali</b> (accept Cassius<b> Clay</b> until mentioned) Page 3", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1999, this country\u2019s soldiers attempted to infiltrate the Line of Control, sparking the Kargil War. Former leaders of this country include Yahya Khan, who launched Operation Searchlight to counter the Awami League, and Benazir Bhutto, the first democratic female leader of a Muslim nation. Muhammad Ali Jinnah founded, for the point, what country whose \u201cEast\u201d portion is now Bangladesh and which contests Kashmir with its neighbor, India?", "answer": "Islamic Republic of<b> Pakistan</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This figure agreed to give a rare interview with Martin Bashir that was first broadcast in November 1995. Pictures of this person wearing a helmet and flak jacket in Angola helped raise awareness of landmine removal efforts. This person was killed alongside driver Henri Paul and Dodi Fayed in a car crash in a Parisian tunnel a year after her highly publicized divorce from Prince Charles. For the point, name this royal activist, the mother of British princes William and Harry.", "answer": "<b> Di</b>ana, Princess of Wales (accept<b> Di</b>ana Spencer; prompt on Spencer)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Nicaragua, noting that the principle of voluntary national commitment did not do enough, refused to join this agreement, which was weakened in June 2017 when Donald Trump declared that the US would leave it. For the point, name this 2016 multinational agreement to reduce carbon emissions that was signed in France.", "answer": "<b> Paris</b> Agreement (or<b> Paris</b> Accord; accept any additional information mentioning climate change)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This event prompted Pope John XXIII to urge governments \u201cnot to remain deaf to this cry of humanity.\u201d During this event, the submarine B-59 refused to open fire, after which Vasili Arkhipov became known as the \u201cman who saved the world.\u201d In the aftermath of this event, Jupiter systems were removed from Turkey and a hotline was established to improve communications between Moscow and Washington. For the point, name this October 1962 event in which Nikita Khrushchev attempted to place missiles in the Caribbean.", "answer": "<b> Cuban Missile</b> Crisis (accept<b> October Crisis</b> before \u201cOctober\u201d is read; accept other terms for \u201ccrisis,\u201d such as \u201cscare\u201d) Page 4", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Henry Flagler\u2019s Overseas Railroad targeted this island chain and operated until 1935. A farcical\u201cConch Republic\u201d was set up in this island chain by Dennis Wardlow in 1982 to protest a series of roadblocks. PanAm was founded in 1927 to fly airmail from one island in this chain to Havana. The Seven Mile Bridge can be found in these islands, whose largest island is named Largo. For the point, name this island chain off the southern coast of Florida.", "answer": "Florida<b> Keys</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "In 1738 in this city\u2019s Aldersgate ward, an intense religious experience at a Moravian church sparked a new denomination. General William Booth founded the Salvation Army in this city, where its headquarters remain. The first Methodist conference was held under John Wesley\u2019s leadership in this city, where a statue of Wesley stands in the churchyard of a cathedral rebuilt by Christopher Wren. For the point, name this city where St. Paul\u2019s Cathedral hosts Anglican services.", "answer": "<b> London</b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This location partially titles a memoir that usually goes by the shortened name<em> Mourt\u2019s Relation</em>, which was written by Edward Winslow. A plantation in this location names a book about a group of colonists governed for thirty years by William Bradford, its author. Each of those works describe the traditional \u201cfirst Thanksgiving,\u201d which took place in this location in 1621. For the point, name this New England where the Purtians of the<em> Mayflower</em> settled near a namesake rock.", "answer": "<b> Plymouth</b> (accept<b> Plymouth</b> Colony,<b> Plymouth</b> Rock,<b> Plymouth</b> Plantation, etc.; prompt on New England)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Thousands of people were injured or killed in a stampede during this ruler\u2019s coronation feast at Khodynka Field, helping earn him the epithet \u201cBloody.\u201d This ruler issued the October Manifesto, establishing the first state Duma, after the 1905 Revolution. Numerous losses in both the Russo-Japanese War and World War I led this ruler to abdicate in favor of his brother Michael. For the point, name this Romanov ruler, the last Russian tsar, who was killed with his family in 1918.", "answer": "<b> Nicholas II</b> Page 5", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Euclid proved that the diagonal of one of these shapes is irrational and equal to their side length times two to the one-half power. Ben Franklin popularized \u201cmagic\u201d arrays of numbers in this shape. For the point, name these shapes whose four sides all have the same length.", "answer": "<b> square</b>s (accept<b> squaring</b> the circle; accept<b> magic square</b>s; do not accept or prompt on other shapes)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {"question": "This dynasty is honored on the Mansu Hill Grand Monument, which depicts Mount Paektu. The founder of this dynasty outlined the concept of Juche [joo-chay] and created a cult of personality. A member of this family was arrested attempting to visit Disneyland in Japan; that member was assassinated in Kuala Lumpur\u2019s airport in 2016. For the point, name this ruling family of North Korea that includes Il-sung, Jong-il, and Jong-un.", "answer": "<b> Kim</b> family (or dynasty, etc.) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Leo the Isaurian ended the first of this empire\u2019s Iconoclasms. Embellished or fake political scandals in this empire were detailed in Procopius\u2019<em> Secret History</em>. The Sassanians and this empire established the Eternal Peace, and its expansion was checked by the Seljuks at Manzikert. The Fourth Crusade was diverted and instead sacked the capital of, for the point, what empire that was once ruled by Justinian the Great from Constantinople?", "answer": "<b> Byzantine</b> Empire (accept<b> Eastern Roman</b> Empire) Page 6", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}